let's now move into a discussion about why
multiprocessor hardware
plays a role when it comes to scheduling and
why it actually
makes it more complicated
let's start discussing the concept / the
role that caches have
it so here we have three different organizations
of CPU
and memory
we have an initial one the first one here
in which we just
have two CPUs and they have some shared memory
they can
access then we have a second one in which
we have the same
thing but now each CPU has also private cache
so some smaller memory where it can keep recent
data that
is accessing
so for example a block of instructions so that
when you
need to fetch the next instruction you have
it already there
instead of just going back and forth every
time from the
memory but in practice you can even have something
like
the third one which is even more complicated
so you have both private memories caches that
are also dedicated
to differents CPUs and then you have also
the shared memory
this is actually how modern architectures
look like
so if you assume we are in one of these setups
let say either
b or c
now you can see that you might have a process
that is running
on this CPU
the second one this one it
issues a request
for input output so it goes into the waiting
state
now since it was the process was running here
he probably
had some data in the cache
and if the cash was not cleared when we want
to run the process
again it might actually be beneficial for
its performance
to get back to the same CPU because it will
find already
some things in the cash
and since they are there there is no need
to go through
the bus here and go back to the main memory
to fetch the
data but of course if we reschedule the process
but instead
of this CPU we send it to another CPU not a
big deal
i mean it will still work but since there
is nothing in
the cache from the previous execution it will
need to go
to main memory and take stuff back to the
cache
so you see that if you want to achieve better
performance
you might want to try to replace processes
back to the same
CPU they were running
but of course everything comes with a price
so if you want to do something like this then
you need at
least to keep additional information about
which process is
being scheduled in which CPU so that you send
it back there
it's also more complicated than that because
it might be
that you have a lot of free CPUs but just
the one you
want it's actually used by another process
what should you do then go to another one
or maybe wait a
bit and see if it gets free and place again the
process on the
same CPU not important right now how you solve
this
in practice it depends on how the operating
system is implemented
but what I'm trying to say here is that you
see that as soon
as you bring in multicore architectures and
their actual placement
of memories if you want to be efficient if
you want your
scheduling to perform well then you start
having a lot of
challenges you don't have with a single core
single CPU
architecture let's move to the next one
there was something more I wanted to say here
in fact if you are familiar with c programming
you know
that you can specify when you run
when you start a process you can tell the
operating system
that you want this process to be pinned to
a specific core
in that case the operating system is only
allowed to use
that core for running the process even if
there are context
switches in between
and now you can see that this is done for
performance because
you know that since you always use the same
code you also
have access to the same memories and caches
and so on
so there are higher chances that you don't
have to go to
the main memory to fetch back your data but
you can use
your local cache
we have other types of architectures the non
uniform memory
architectures so inside a computer we can
have different
sockets each socket can have its own CPU and
each CPU can
have multiple physical cores
and this is what is being shown in this image
so we have four sockets and each of the four
CPUs has
four cores
now within each socket the CPUs can share
their own memory
but they can also communicate with other CPUs
so this is non-uniform because as you can
see if C1 and
C2 want to share some data they can do
it through their
own memory
so it's faster than if C1 here and C1
here need to share
something because they need inter-socket communication
and this is another challenge
so if you want to schedule two threads and
you know that
these have a behavior that could resemble that
of a producer
and a consumer assuming you know this then
it might be
more beneficial to place these two in cores
that belong
to the same socket because then the number
of memories they
need to go through to communicate is smaller
and they
can use their own memory
so like in the green case than in the red
one
but again you need is extra information to
maintain extra
information about the threads and the processes
if you want to do this to improve the performance
achieved by your scheduling strategy
and of course there is an extra challenge
here
that is how would you know the two threads
are a producer and
a consumer?
if it's a general system an interactive system
you don't
know what is going to run might not really
notice there are
specific cases in a batch  system
for example you might know what processes
you are running
and you might know that many of them have
this kind of relation
so you can take better decisions based on
this
but in general you wouldn't know